Alright, welcome to the Ultimate Choice Challenge.
さあ、究極の選択チャレンジへようこそ。
Today, we're going to tackle one super useful English word.
今日はとても便利な英単語を学びます。
Think of it like a new superpower for asking awesome questions.
素晴らしい質問をするための新しいスーパーパワーのようなものです。
You ready? Okay, first up, the ultimate question. Cats or dogs?
準備はいいですか？まずは究極の質問。猫と犬、どちらが好きですか？
It's a huge debate, right? Everyone has an opinion.
大きな議論ですよね？みんな意見があります。
Well, life is packed with choices just like this.
実際、人生はこのような選択であふれています。
And today, we're going to learn the perfect word for asking about them.
今日はそれについて尋ねるための完璧な単語を学びます。
And that magic word is... Witch!
その魔法の言葉は…「どちら」です！
Now, I know in Japanese you've got dōtra for two things and dōrei for three or more,
日本語では二つのものに「どちら」、三つ以上には「どれ」を使いますが、
but get this. In English, it's way easier.
英語ではもっと簡単です。
We just use which for everything.
私たちは「which」をすべてに使います。
Whether it's two choices or twenty, which is the word you need?
二つの選択でも二十の選択でも、必要なのは「which」です。
Alright, time to start the challenge.
さあ、チャレンジを始めましょう。
Welcome to level one, the basic choice.
レベル1へようこそ、基本の選択です。
We're going to keep it simple and focus on questions using the word is.
シンプルに「is」を使った質問に焦点を当てます。
Let's do this! See how easy that is?
さあ、やってみましょう！簡単ですよね？
It doesn't matter how many things there are.
物の数は関係ありません。
If you see two bags, you can ask, which is Ken's bag?
二つのバッグがあれば、「どちらがケンのバッグですか？」と聞けます。
If you see a whole bunch of pencils, you just ask, which is your pencil?
たくさんの鉛筆があれば、「どれがあなたの鉛筆ですか？」と聞くだけです。
Same word every time. So simple, right?
毎回同じ単語です。とても簡単ですよね？
And this works for bigger groups too. You know, like the four seasons?
これが大きなグループにも使えます。四季のように。
We've got spring, summer, fall, and winter.
春、夏、秋、冬があります。
So if you want to ask your friend to pick their favorite, what do you say?
友達に好きな季節を選んでもらうには、何と言いますか？
You got it. Which is your favorite season?
そうです。「どれがあなたの好きな季節ですか？」です。
Now what if you want to give someone specific choices? Easy.
では、特定の選択肢を与えたい場合は？簡単です。
You just add or at the end.
最後に「or」を加えるだけです。
Which is your favorite color? Pink or blue? It's super direct and people use it all the time.
「どれがあなたの好きな色ですか？ピンクか青？」と聞けば、直接的で、みんな使っています。
Awesome work on level one. You're crushing it. But are you ready for level two? It's time for
レベル1の素晴らしい仕事です。素晴らしいですね。でも、レベル2の準備はできていますか？次は
the action choice. This is where we learn how to ask about choices that involve doing stuff,
アクション選択です。ここでは、行動を伴う選択について尋ねる方法を学びます。
using our little helper words do and does. So how do we build these questions?
「do」と「does」を使います。これらの質問をどう作るか見てみましょう。
Let's break it down. You start with a basic sentence, like, you like summer. Simple enough.
基本的な文から始めます。「あなたは夏が好きです。」簡単ですね。
To make it a yes-no question, you pop do at the front, do you like summer?
これをイエス・ノーの質問にするには、「do」を前に置きます。「あなたは夏が好きですか？」
But now, to ask about a choice, you just swap out summer for our hero word, which, and put
そして、選択について尋ねるには、夏を「which」に置き換え、
it at the very beginning, so it becomes which do you like?
最初に持ってくると「どれが好きですか？」になります。
So here's the secret recipe, you ready?
では、秘密のレシピを教えます。準備はいいですか？
Just remember this simple formula.
このシンプルな公式を覚えておいてください。
Start with which, then add do or does.
「which」で始めて、次に「do」か「does」を加えます。
After that comes the person, you, she, they, whatever.
その後に人を入れます。「あなた」「彼女」「彼ら」など。
the action word, like, need, eat.
次に動詞、例えば「必要」「食べる」。
And you finish it off with a question mark. Boom!
最後に疑問符を付けます。完璧な質問ができます。
A perfect question every time.
毎回完璧な質問です。
Okay, let's try it out with something you know very well, school subjects.
では、よく知っている学校の科目で試してみましょう。
Which do you like? English or math? See?
「どれが好きですか？英語か数学？」どうですか？
It's that same A or B thing we just talked about. Easy peasy.
さっき話したAかBの選択ですね。簡単です。
Here's another one. Which does she eat for breakfast? Cereal or toast?
もう一つ。彼女は朝食に何を食べますか？シリアルかトースト？
And speaking of cereal, this is a perfect window into American culture.
シリアルについて言えば、これはアメリカ文化への完璧な窓です。
Seriously, if you walk into a supermarket in the US, there's literally an entire aisle,
本当に、アメリカのスーパーに入ると、シリアル専用の通路が一つあります。
a whole row just for cereal, hundreds of boxes.
シリアルの箱が何百も並んでいます。
So yeah, you're definitely going to need the word which to survive breakfast.
だから、朝食を生き延びるためには「which」が絶対に必要です。
Okay, you've mastered the basics. You've handled the action questions.
基本をマスターしましたね。アクションの質問もこなしました。
It is time to power up for level three, the pro level question.
さあ、レベル3、プロレベルの質問にパワーアップする時です。
This is a really cool trick to make your questions sound even more natural.
これは、質問をさらに自然に聞こえさせるための素晴らしいテクニックです。
All you do is add a noun right after which.
「which」の後に名詞を加えるだけです。
So let's look at the difference.
違いを見てみましょう。
You could ask, which do you like, tea or coffee?
「どれが好きですか？お茶かコーヒー？」と聞くことができます。
And that's totally fine. Nothing wrong with it. But check this out.
それでも全然問題ありません。でも、これを見てください。
Which drink do you like, tea or coffee? See that?
「どの飲み物が好きですか？お茶かコーヒー？」どうですか？
By adding the word drink, you're telling the person exactly what category you're talking
「飲み物」という言葉を加えることで、相手に何のカテゴリーについて話しているかを明確に伝えています。
about. It's a tiny change, but it makes you sound super clear.
小さな変更ですが、非常にクリアに聞こえます。
So here's the big rule for this level.
これがこのレベルの大きなルールです。
Which and the noun that comes after it are like best friends.
「Which」とその後に続く名詞は 親友のような関係です。
They stick together always.
いつも一緒にいます。
Think of them as one single piece, one big question word.
彼らを一つの大きな疑問詞として 考えてください。
And that piece always goes at the start of the sentence.
その疑問詞は文の最初に来ます。
Let's try another one.
もう一つ試してみましょう。
Instead of just saying which do you like, you can get more specific.
「Which do you like?」だけでなく、 もっと具体的に聞けます。
Which subject do you like, music or art? So much clearer, right?
「Which subject do you like, music or art?」 ずっと明確ですよね？
It just sounds a little more pro. Wow! You did it!
少しプロっぽく聞こえます。すごい！ あなたはやりました！
You battled through level 1, 2, and 3.
レベル1、2、3をクリアしました。
But now, you must face the final boss, the Recap Challenge.
でも今、最後のボス、 リキャップチャレンジに挑まなければなりません。
It's time to review all the awesome skills you've just unlocked.
今まで習った素晴らしいスキルを 復習する時間です。
Okay, think of this as your ultimate cheat sheet.
これを究極のチートシートと考えてください。
We've got everything right here.
すべてここにあります。
We started simple with which is, right?
まずは「which is」から始めましたよね？
Then we learned how to add choices with a or b.
次に、選択肢を「a or b」で 追加する方法を学びました。
After that, we leveled up to action questions with do and does.
その後、「do」や「does」を使った アクション質問にレベルアップしました。
And finally, we hit the pro level by adding a noun after which to get super specific.
最後に、「which」の後に名詞を 加えて、さらに具体的にしました。
So to wrap things up, I've got one last question for you.
まとめとして、最後の質問があります。
Using that pro level skill we just learned, it's about two sports that are huge in
今学んだプロレベルのスキルを使って、 日本とアメリカで人気のある2つのスポーツについてです。
Japan and in America. Ready?
「Which sport do you like, baseball or basketball?」 どうですか？
Which sport do you like, baseball or basketball? See?
あなたは完全にできています。
You've totally got this.
これで、考えられる選択肢について 質問する力を手に入れました。
You now have all the power you need to ask about any choice you can think of.
素晴らしい仕事でした。さあ、外に出て 質問を始めましょう。